<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
   xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
   xml:id="amp-transcript__0034.xml"
   xml:base="https://id.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/auden-musulin-papers">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="s">Auden Musulin Papers: A Digital Edition of W. H. Auden´s Letters to Stella Musulin (FWF P 33754)</title>
            <title level="a">Typed Letter Signed Michael O'Sullivan to Stella Musulin 1984-05-31</title>
            <author>O'Sullivan, Michael</author>
            <editor>
               <name>Mayer, Sandra</name>
               <name>Frühwirth, Timo</name>
            </editor>
            <funder>
               <name>FWF Austrian Science Fund</name>
               <address>
                  <street>Sensengasse 1</street>
                  <postCode>1090 Vienna</postCode>
                  <placeName>
                     <country>A</country>
                     <settlement>Vienna</settlement>
                  </placeName>
               </address>
            </funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>AMP</edition>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and commentary</resp>
               <name>Mayer, Sandra</name>
               <name>Frühwirth, Timo</name>
            </respStmt>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities and Cultural Heritage</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna</pubPlace>
            <date when="2021">2021</date>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/deed.en">
                  <p>You are free to: Share — copy and redistribute the material in any medium or format; adapt — remix, transform, and build upon the material
for any purpose, even commercially.</p>
                  <p>The licensor cannot revoke these freedoms as long as you follow the license terms. Under the following terms:</p>
                  <p>Attribution — You must give appropriate credit, provide a link to the license, and indicate if changes were made. You may do so in any reasonable manner, but not in any way that suggests the licensor endorses you or your use. No additional restrictions — You may not apply legal terms or technological measures that legally restrict others from doing anything the license permits.</p>
                  <p>Notices:</p>
                  <p>You do not have to comply with the license for elements of the material in the public domain or where your use is permitted by an applicable exception or limitation. No warranties are given. The license may not give you all of the permissions necessary for your intended use. For example, other rights such as publicity, privacy, or moral rights may limit how you use the material.</p>
               </licence>
               <p>Copyright literary texts W. H. Auden Estate of W. H. Auden.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <p>Machine-Readable Transcriptions of the Auden Musulin Papers</p>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <listWit>
               <witness n="1">
                  <msDesc>
                     <msIdentifier>
                        <country>A</country>
                        <settlement>St. Pölten</settlement>
                        <repository>State Collections of Lower Austria</repository>
                        <collection>Stella Musulin (Depot)</collection>
                        <idno>2, 14</idno>
                     </msIdentifier>
                     <history>
                        <origin><origDate when-iso="1984-05-31" >1984-05-31</origDate></origin>
                     </history>
                  </msDesc>
               </witness>
            </listWit>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change who="pandorfer" when="2021-09-21">template populated with script "create_templates.py"</change>
         <change who="smayer" when="2021-12-15">text transcribed</change>
         <change who="tfruehwirth" when="2021-12-16">text transcribed using Transkribus</change>
         <change who="smayer tfruehwirth" when="2021-12-16">transcriptions collated</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface ulx="0" uly="0" lrx="5682" lry="7728">
         <graphic url="https://iiif.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/amp/amp_0231/"/>
      </surface>
      <surface ulx="0" uly="0" lrx="5680" lry="7728">
         <graphic url="https://iiif.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/amp/amp_0232/"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         <div xml:id="transcription">
            <pb facs="https://iiif.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/amp/amp_0231/" type="sheet"/>
               <p>
                  UNIVERSITY OF DUBLIN
               </p>
               <p>
                  TRINITY COLLEGE<lb/>
                  DUBLIN 2
               </p>
               <p>
                  Home address :<lb/>
                  22, Kildare Street,<lb/>
                  DUBLIN, 2.<lb/>
                  Tel : 762662.
               </p>
               <p>
                  Tel. 772941
               </p>
               <p>
                  31 : V: 1984
               </p>
               <p>
                  Dear Baroness Musulin,<lb/>
                  I remember you telling me that you liked the novels of<lb/>
                  Molly Keane when I visited you with Peter Muller in October of last year. I<lb/>
                  was delighted to see that Virago Press have decided to reprint her early<lb/>
                  novels and I thought of you when I saw them <del><unclear>o</unclear></del>in the bookshops.  I am sending<lb/>
                  you herewith The Rising Tide - the first in the series of reprints and I very<lb/>
                  much hope you enjoy reading it.<lb/>
                  I remember with great affection our chat about W.H. Auden<lb/>
                  and I am very grateful to you for sharing those memories with me.  Plans for<lb/>
                  the Auden Exhibition in the Kunstlerhaus are now very far advanced.  I have<lb/>
                  put togther a complete collection of Auden's first editions, selections from<lb/>
                  his contributions to periodicals, representative anthologies, his films for<lb/>
                  the G.P.O Film Unit, many items connected with his work for the Group Theatre,<lb/>
                  all the opera libretti, <del><unclear></unclear></del>Britten's arrangements of his poems and many other items.<lb/>
                  I have also arranged for various portraits of Auden to be sent to Vienna ; they<lb/>
                  include Sir William Coldstream<unclear>'</unclear>s 1937 portrait, a portrait by Mervyn Peake painted<lb/>
                  in the same year, two drawings by Maurice Field and a portrait by Don Bachardy.<lb/>
                  I have also managed to get 26 lithographs by Henry Moore which he did in 1973 to<lb/>
                  illustrate a selection of Auden's poems.<lb/>
                  Stephen Spender has agreed to come to Vienna during the<lb/>
                  period of the Exhibition - that is 11th October to 3rd November.  Humphrey<lb/>
                  Carpenter will lecture on Auden at the invitation of the British Council, so it<lb/>
                  all promises to be a splendid celebration of Auden's life and work.<lb/>
                  I was terribly disappointed not to have seen you when I was<lb/>
                  in Vienna in March but alas I was at the mercy of my friends who have cars and,<lb/>
                  as luck would have it,they were all so busy at various things I was left stranded in<lb/>
                  Vienna throughout my brief visit.  However I shall be spending September, October<lb/>
                  and November in Austria and I very much look forward to seeing you then.<lb/>
                  I had a letter from Edward Mendelson yesterday and he asked<lb/>
                  me to send you his very best wishes which I do along with my own.  I hope this<lb/>
                  finds you in good spirits and that Summer is <del><unclear></unclear></del> better behaved in Austria <del><unclear></unclear></del>than<lb/>
                  it is here in Ireland.<lb/>
                  With all good wishes,<lb/>
                  Yours very sincerely,<lb/>
                  Mich<unclear>ae</unclear>l <unclear>O'Sullivan</unclear><lb/>
                  MICHAEL O'SULLIVAN.
               </p>
            <pb facs="https://iiif.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/amp/amp_0232/" type="sheet"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>