<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xml:id="amp-transcript__0031.xml" xml:base="https://auden-musulin-papers.github.io/amp-app" prev="https://auden-musulin-papers.github.io/amp-app/amp-transcript__0030.xml" next="https://auden-musulin-papers.github.io/amp-app/amp-transcript__0032.xml">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="s">Auden Musulin Papers: A Digital Edition of W. H. Auden´s Letters to Stella Musulin (FWF P 33754)</title>
            <title level="a">Typed Letter Stella Musulin to Edward Mendelson 1985-12-15</title>
            <author>Musulin, Stella</author>
            <editor>
               <name>Mayer, Sandra</name>
               <name>Frühwirth, Timo</name>
            </editor>
            <funder>
               <name>FWF Austrian Science Fund</name>
               <address>
                  <street>Sensengasse 1</street>
                  <postCode>1090 Vienna</postCode>
                  <placeName>
                     <country>A</country>
                     <settlement>Vienna</settlement>
                  </placeName>
               </address>
            </funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>AMP</edition>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and commentary</resp>
               <name>Mayer, Sandra</name>
               <name>Frühwirth, Timo</name>
            </respStmt>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities and Cultural Heritage</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna</pubPlace>
            <date when="2021">2021</date>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/deed.en">
                  <p>You are free to: Share — copy and redistribute the material in any medium or format; adapt — remix, transform, and build upon the material
for any purpose, even commercially.</p>
                  <p>The licensor cannot revoke these freedoms as long as you follow the license terms. Under the following terms:</p>
                  <p>Attribution — You must give appropriate credit, provide a link to the license, and indicate if changes were made. You may do so in any reasonable manner, but not in any way that suggests the licensor endorses you or your use. No additional restrictions — You may not apply legal terms or technological measures that legally restrict others from doing anything the license permits.</p>
                  <p>Notices:</p>
                  <p>You do not have to comply with the license for elements of the material in the public domain or where your use is permitted by an applicable exception or limitation. No warranties are given. The license may not give you all of the permissions necessary for your intended use. For example, other rights such as publicity, privacy, or moral rights may limit how you use the material.</p>
               </licence>
               <p>Copyright literary texts W. H. Auden Estate of W. H. Auden.</p>
            </availability>
         <idno type="handle">https://hdl.handle.net/21.11115/0000-000E-C324-D</idno></publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <p>Machine-Readable Transcriptions of the Auden Musulin Papers</p>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <listWit>
               <witness n="1">
                  <msDesc>
                     <msIdentifier>
                        <country>A</country>
                        <settlement>St. Pölten</settlement>
                        <repository>State Collections of Lower Austria</repository>
                        <collection>Stella Musulin (Depot)</collection>
                        <idno>2, 11</idno>
                     </msIdentifier>
                     <history>
                        <origin><origDate when-iso="1985-12-15">1985-12-15</origDate></origin>
                     </history>
                  </msDesc>
               </witness>
            </listWit>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change who="pandorfer" when="2021-09-21">template populated with script "create_templates.py"</change>
         <change who="smayer" when="2021-12-14">text transcribed</change>
         <change who="tfruehwirth" when="2021-12-14">text transcribed using Transkribus</change>
         <change who="smayer tfruehwirth" when="2021-12-14">transcriptions collated</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface ulx="0" uly="0" lrx="5696" lry="7770">
         <graphic url="https://iiif.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/amp/amp_0223/"/>
      </surface>
      <surface ulx="0" uly="0" lrx="5700" lry="7766">
         <graphic url="https://iiif.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/amp/amp_0224/"/>
      </surface>
      <surface ulx="0" uly="0" lrx="5702" lry="7776">
         <graphic url="https://iiif.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/amp/amp_0225/"/>
      </surface>
      <surface ulx="0" uly="0" lrx="5698" lry="7766">
         <graphic url="https://iiif.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/amp/amp_0226/"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         <div xml:id="transcription">
            <pb facs="https://iiif.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/amp/amp_0223/" type="sheet"/>
               <p>
                  Fridau<lb/>
                  A-3200 Obergrafendorf<lb/>
                  bei St.Pölten, Austria.<lb/>
                  15 De<del>d</del>cember 1985.
               </p>
               <p>
                  Dear Ed,<lb/>
                  The time has come to send out a signal to you from this<lb/>
                  ancient, scandal-ridden, provincial dump.  Peter Müller has<lb/>
                  not been sleeping over his plan to edit a book on Auden´s<lb/>
                  time here, he has been writing books himself in addition to<lb/>
                  his full time profession.  Now - you may know this - it is<lb/>
                  definite and the book is to come out in February 1987 in<lb/>
                  time for A´s 80th.<lb/>
                  So he got me back to my desk, to, in his words, combine<lb/>
                  my English and German texts, and bring the whole thing up to<lb/>
                  date.  "Write as fully as you can, double the length."  I<lb/>
                  protested that a) I don´t wish to chatter more feebly than I<lb/>
                  have already, b) I am ancient and frail, also lazy, c) the<lb/>
                  first MSS only approximate to each other while containing m<del><gap/></del>kuch<lb/>
                  the same material;  their tone differs.  But above all they<lb/>
                  have, whether bad or indifferent, a certain shape or form and<lb/>
                  you cannot just stuff more material into it which refers to<lb/>
                  things which hap<del>e</del>pened subsequently.  So we agreed that we would<lb/>
                  leave the texts to stand and that I would say, roughly, okay,<lb/>
                  that was how it looked then;  what has happened since, what<lb/>
                  is there still be said by us, who knew Auden in Kirchstetten<lb/>
                  in view of the fact that Carpenter did no research on this<lb/>
                  location<unclear>s</unclear>?  For a long time the idea was only to write a<lb/>
                  German text, I mean that the book would be sol<del>t´</del>ely German<lb/>
                  l<del>n</del>anguage production, and this I thought until quite recently.<lb/>
                  Suddenly, Peter bounced me with the comment that he would<lb/>
                  "like an English version as well."  I had thought my two texts<lb/>
                  were only to be combined and the sequel written in German.<lb/>
                  This presents technical problems.  For example, and now my<lb/>
                  questions to you begin:<lb/>
                  We ihave here a copy of Auden´s declaration to the tax<lb/>
                  authorities.  (I have been determined all along that this<lb/>
                  document should be published AND RIGHT HERE.  Apart from making<lb/>
                  Them look stupid, it must be unique in literary history that a<lb/>
                  great poet should explain to the tax authorities how poetry<lb/>
                  comes to be written.)  Do you have the English original, or where<lb/>
                  is it;  did it ever exist or was the German drafted by Auden<lb/>
                  and put together by, s<del>y</del>ay, his lawyer?  Or could this have been<lb/>
                  done by whoever it was who wrote the prose version of the<lb/>
                  Weinheber poem?  I have that text which A. gave me, but there<lb/>
                  is no record of who wrote it.  In my first dr<del>s</del>aft of the talk<lb/>
                  given at the PEN Club in London in 1976 I wrote: "I have the<lb/>
                  statement in German translation, so that what I am reading is<lb/>
                  my own re-translation back into English and not the original.<lb/>
                  I should be very grateful if you could help me over the<lb/>
                  address which Auden held at Neulengbach.  I have the original<lb/>
                  English text which to my horror Auden asked me to translate:<lb/>
                  although capable of creative writing in German, to deal with<lb/>
                  this tough text was too m<del>k</del>uch and it was corrected by my husband.<lb/>
                  Müller possesses the German text taken from a tape.  Now this<lb/>
                  English text is so familia<del>s</del>rrto me that it deafens me to all<lb/>
                  or any sources.  A digest of it is in the PEN text but I wonder
               </p>
            <pb facs="https://iiif.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/amp/amp_0224/" type="sheet"/>
            <pb facs="https://iiif.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/amp/amp_0225/" type="sheet"/>
               <p>
                  - 2 -<lb/>
                  to what extent Auden´s speech contains hitherto unknown material,<lb/>
                  if any.  I said air<del>l</del>ily that he had probably said i<del>a</del>t a<del>s</del>ll before,<lb/>
                  in Secondary Worlds and so on, but this is not true.  After a<lb/>
                  preamble the speech begins:<lb/>
                  Between the ages of six and twelve, I spent a great many of<lb/>
                  my waking hours in the fabrication of a private secondary<lb/>
                  s   sacred world, the basic elements of which were a) a limestone<lb/>
                  landscape mainly derived from the Pennine Moors in the North of<lb/>
                  England and b) an industry - lead-mining.<lb/>
                  I<del>r</del>t is no doubt psychologically significant that my sacred<lb/>
                  world was autistic - that is to say I had no wish to share<lb/>
                  it with others ...   and so on.<lb/>
                  He goes on to define the Primary and Secondary Worlds;  his<lb/>
                  private world, the restrictions on the freedom of the artist;<lb/>
                  water-turbines, his Platonic idea of a concentrating mill and<lb/>
                  of his moral duty to sacrifice his aesthetic <del>princip </del>preference<lb/>
                  to reality or truth.<lb/>
                  If you like I can have the whole thing photo-copied and<lb/>
                  send it along, but you see what it´s about.  I cannot believe<lb/>
                  that Wystan chose Neulengbach to make a one-time-only<lb/>
                  statement of this length and weight, the idea is absurd and<lb/>
                  the point of my quotation in my talk in 1976 was to show Auden<lb/>
                  in one aspect of his contact with the Austrians, not without<lb/>
                  a touch of hilarity.  But this is not in Secondary Worlds,<lb/>
                  I have leafed through your Early Auden page by page and finkd<lb/>
                  no reference, nor can I find it anywhere else.  Can you<lb/>
                  el<del>i</del>ucidate?<lb/>
                  M<del>Y</del>y worm´s eye view of the arrangements for the funeral<lb/>
                  goes iknto my new piece, and incidentally the contributions<lb/>
                  will be looked over by a lawyer.<lb/>
                  Are you about to come out with a Middle Auden or whatever?<lb/>
                  If so it would be nice to know about it so I can refer to it.<lb/>
                  The chaplain sto the British Embassy in Vienna gave me the<lb/>
                  name and addre<del>e</del>ss of the clergyman who took the service with the<lb/>
                  RC pasrish priest and I wrote to him to find o<del>iu</del>ut´whether he<lb/>
                  can remember the form of service etc. but no answer so far.<lb/>
                  This would be of interest here because though common practice<lb/>
                  in England such an ecumenical service was a novelty here and<lb/>
                  caused much comment.<lb/>
                  How are you and what are you doing apa<del>s</del>rt from teaching?<lb/>
                  I had a lot of illness, hospitals etc. but am now stab<del>l</del>ilised<lb/>
                  and am living now wholly in the country but am well looked<lb/>
                  after and see plenty of people.  It´s Parkinson´s disease<lb/>
                  which can be kept pretty well under control these days.  My<lb/>
                  relations organised a splendid surprise party for my 70th<lb/>
                  birthday which went on all day, at breakfast I didn´t yet<lb/>
                  know <del>t</del>what lay ahead.  My son plotted this and steered it from<lb/>
                  New York but was there on the day.  He built up the Austrian<lb/>
                  bank Creditanstalt-Bankverein in NY, and if ever you need to<lb/>
                  send me bulky papers or whatever - not that you will - contact<lb/>
                  him at 212-702-9101.  His <del>m</del>name is Marko.<lb/>
                  Good health and suc<unclear>c</unclear>ess i<del>j</del>n 1986,
               </p>
            <pb facs="https://iiif.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/amp/amp_0226/" type="sheet"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>