<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
   xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
   xml:id="project_description_0001.xml">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Editorial Declaration</title>
            <author>
               <name>Mayer, Sandra</name>
               <name>Frühwirth, Timo</name>
            </author>
            <funder>
               <name>FWF Austrian Science Fund</name>
               <address>
                  <street>Sensengasse 1</street>
                  <postCode>1090 Vienna</postCode>
                  <placeName>
                     <country>A</country>
                     <settlement>Vienna</settlement>
                  </placeName>
               </address>
            </funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities and Cultural Heritage</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna</pubPlace>
            <date when="2022">2022</date>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/deed.en">
                  <p>You are free to: Share — copy and redistribute the material in any medium or format; adapt — remix, transform, and build upon the material
                     for any purpose, even commercially.</p>
                  <p>The licensor cannot revoke these freedoms as long as you follow the license terms. Under the following terms:</p>
                  <p>Attribution — You must give appropriate credit, provide a link to the license, and indicate if changes were made. You may do so in any reasonable manner, but not in any way that suggests the licensor endorses you or your use. No additional restrictions — You may not apply legal terms or technological measures that legally restrict others from doing anything the license permits.</p>
                  <p>Notices:</p>
                  <p>You do not have to comply with the license for elements of the material in the public domain or where your use is permitted by an applicable exception or limitation. No warranties are given. The license may not give you all of the permissions necessary for your intended use. For example, other rights such as publicity, privacy, or moral rights may limit how you use the material.</p>
               </licence>
               <p>Copyright literary texts W. H. Auden Estate of W. H. Auden.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>born digital</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">English</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change who="smayer tfruehwirth" when="2022-02-24">text created</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div>
            <head>Editorial Declaration</head>
            <p></p>
            <div>
               <head>Transcription Guidelines</head>
               <div>
                  <head>
                     1. Diplomatic transcriptions represent the spelling, punctuation, layout, and revisions as they appear, with minimal editorial intervention or interpretation.
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     1.1. Spelling<lb/>
                     1.1.1. The original spelling in both manuscripts and typescripts is retained, even if irregular (example: Autograph Letter Signed W. H. Auden to Stella Musulin with Typescript W. H. Auden "Freedom and Necessity in the Arts" 1970-05-21, page 9, line 8).<lb/>
                     1.1.2. Signs that cannot be transcribed with certainty are marked up as <![CDATA[<]]>unclear<![CDATA[>]]> in XML and represented in grey on the web page (example: Autograph Letter Signed W. H. Auden to Stella Musulin 1973-09-24, page 3, line 9).<lb/>
                     1.1.3. Manuscript signs are not marked up as 'unclear' when they can be identified as a consistent and typical feature of the respective author's handwriting (example: "address", Autograph Letter Signed W. H. Auden to Stella Musulin 1968-10-15, page 3, line 25).<lb/>
                     1.1.4. Signatures are not marked up as 'unclear'.<lb/>
                     1.1.5. Signs that cannot be transcribed are marked up as <![CDATA[<]]>gap<![CDATA[>]]> in XML and represented by means of grey square brackets on the web page (example: Autograph Letter Signed W. H. Auden to Stella Musulin 1968-10-12, page 3, line 7).
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     1.2. Numericals<lb/>
                     1.2.1. For typescripts, the characters 'I' (uppercase i) and 'O' (uppercase o) designating the numbers 1 and 0 (zero), respectively, are preserved.
                     1.2.2. For manuscripts, the anglophone variant writing of the numeral 1 is represented by '1'.
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     1.3. Punctuation and Spaces<lb/>
                     1.3.1. The original punctuation and spaces are retained, even if irregular (example: Autograph Letter Signed W. H. Auden to Stella Musulin 1968-10-12, page 3, line 4).<lb/>
                     1.3.2. Punctuation signs that cannot be transcribed with certainty are rendered by UTF-8/Unicode symbols that represent a graphical approximation, marked up as <![CDATA[<]]>unclear<![CDATA[>]]> in XML, and represented in grey on the web page (example: Autograph Letter Signed W. H. Auden to Stella Musulin 1965-09-29, page 3, line 16).<lb/>
                     1.3.3. When spaces before or after punctuation marks are significantly smaller than the spaces separating words in the surrounding text, no spaces are transcribed (example: Letter W. H. Auden to Stella Musulin 1962-09-11, page 3, line 12).<lb/>
                     1.3.4. For manuscripts, the length of spaces between words is regularized (example: Autograph Letter Signed W. H. Auden to Stella Musulin 1968-10-12, page 3, line 6).<lb/>
                     1.3.5. For typescripts, the number of spaces within sentences is preserved and marked up as <![CDATA[<]]>space<![CDATA[>]]> in XML (example: Typescript Stella Musulin "In Retrospect" [?], page 1, line 2).
                     1.3.6. In typescripts, line-inital spaces are preserved and marked up as <![CDATA[<]]>space<![CDATA[>]]> if they can plausibly be interpreted as indentations.
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     1.4. Original line breaks and divisions between blocks of text are retained.
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     1.5. Underline
                     1.5.1. Underlines are marked up as <![CDATA[<]]>hi rend="underline"<![CDATA[>]]> and graphically represented on the web page.
                     1.5.2. Underlines are not represented if the form part of signatures.
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     1.6. Characters whose legibility is impaired by smudges and overwritings are marked up as <![CDATA[<]]>unclear<![CDATA[>]]> in XML and represented in grey on the web page.
                  </p>   
                  <p>
                     1.7. Revisions<lb/>
                     1.7.1. The transcriptions represent deletions of text (example: Autograph Letter Signed W. H. Auden to Stella Musulin 1964-12-23, page 3, line 26).<lb/>
                     1.7.2. For overwritings in typescripts, we have accepted the orthographically or grammatically accurate versions as corrections, even if the actual sequences of textual layers cannot be reconstructed (example: Typescript Stella Musulin "In Retrospect" [?], page 1, line 27).
                     1.7.3. For transcriptions of typescripts, we accept the use of the signs 'x', 'm', 'z', and '-' as indicating deletions where such deletion seems plausible.
                     1.7.4. When additions are inserted into manuscripts or typescripts, surrounding spaces are included in ways that are coherent with the general use of spaces in the respective texts (that especially concerns spaces after punctuation in typescripts).
                     1.7.5. When additions replace deleted words in typescripts, they are inserted directly after the deletions without additional spaces.
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     1.8. Pre-printed Components and Postal Additions<lb/>
                     1.8.1. Pre-printed letter heads and sender addresses are transcribed (example: Autograph Letter Signed W. H. Auden to Stella Musulin 1968-10-06, page 2, lines 1-3).<lb/>
                     1.8.2. Image captions in postcards are transcribed (example: Autograph Note Signed Michael O'Sullivan to Stella Musulin [?], page 1, lines 1-2, 12-15).<lb/>
                     1.8.3. Postmarks and stamps are not transcribed.<lb/>
                     1.8.4. Pre-printed postal text and images in telegrams and aerograms are not rendered in the transcriptions (example: Telegram W. H. Auden to Stella Musulin 1971-05-13).
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <head>
                     2. Reading views represent more easily readable versions of diplomatic transcriptions.<!-- see Complete Works VI xiii-xiv for regularization -->
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     2.1. The use of multiple spaces in typescripts is regularized and represented as a single space on the web page.<lb/>
                     2.2. Underlined text in manuscripts and typescripts is italicized in accordance with editing practices applied in <hi rend="italic">The Complete Works of W. H. Auden</hi> edited by Edward Mendelson.<lb/>
                     2.3. The reading views do not represent deletions, but the text as corrected or added.<lb/>
                     
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head></head>
               <p></p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head></head>
               <p></p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>