<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
   xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
   xml:id="amp-transcript__0027.xml"
   xml:base="https://id.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/auden-musulin-papers">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="s">Auden Musulin Papers: A Digital Edition of W. H. Auden´s Letters to Stella Musulin (FWF P 33754)</title>
            <title level="a">Typescript W. H. Auden "Freedom and Necessity in the Arts" [1970]</title>
            <author>Auden, W. H.</author>
            <editor>
               <name>Mayer, Sandra</name>
               <name>Frühwirth, Timo</name>
            </editor>
            <funder>
               <name>FWF Austrian Science Fund</name>
               <address>
                  <street>Sensengasse 1</street>
                  <postCode>1090 Vienna</postCode>
                  <placeName>
                     <country>A</country>
                     <settlement>Vienna</settlement>
                  </placeName>
               </address>
            </funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>AMP</edition>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and commentary</resp>
               <name>Mayer, Sandra</name>
               <name>Frühwirth, Timo</name>
            </respStmt>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities and Cultural Heritage</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Vienna</pubPlace>
            <date when="2021">2021</date>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/deed.en">
                  <p>You are free to: Share — copy and redistribute the material in any medium or format; adapt — remix, transform, and build upon the material
for any purpose, even commercially.</p>
                  <p>The licensor cannot revoke these freedoms as long as you follow the license terms. Under the following terms:</p>
                  <p>Attribution — You must give appropriate credit, provide a link to the license, and indicate if changes were made. You may do so in any reasonable manner, but not in any way that suggests the licensor endorses you or your use. No additional restrictions — You may not apply legal terms or technological measures that legally restrict others from doing anything the license permits.</p>
                  <p>Notices:</p>
                  <p>You do not have to comply with the license for elements of the material in the public domain or where your use is permitted by an applicable exception or limitation. No warranties are given. The license may not give you all of the permissions necessary for your intended use. For example, other rights such as publicity, privacy, or moral rights may limit how you use the material.</p>
               </licence>
               <p>Copyright literary texts W. H. Auden Estate of W. H. Auden.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <p>Machine-Readable Transcriptions of the Auden Musulin Papers</p>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <listWit>
               <witness n="1">
                  <msDesc>
                     <msIdentifier>
                        <country>A</country>
                        <settlement>St. Pölten</settlement>
                        <repository>State Collections of Lower Austria</repository>
                        <collection>Stella Musulin (Depot)</collection>
                        <idno>2, 4</idno>
                     </msIdentifier>
                     <history>
                        <origin><origDate>[1970]</origDate></origin>
                     </history>
                  </msDesc>
               </witness>
            </listWit>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change who="pandorfer" when="2021-09-21">template populated with script "create_templates.py"</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface ulx="0" uly="0" lrx="5708" lry="7736">
         <graphic url="https://iiif.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/amp/amp_0155/"/>
      </surface>
      <surface ulx="0" uly="0" lrx="5706" lry="7738">
         <graphic url="https://iiif.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/amp/amp_0156/"/>
      </surface>
      <surface ulx="0" uly="0" lrx="5706" lry="7740">
         <graphic url="https://iiif.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/amp/amp_0157/"/>
      </surface>
      <surface ulx="0" uly="0" lrx="5704" lry="7746">
         <graphic url="https://iiif.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/amp/amp_0158/"/>
      </surface>
      <surface ulx="0" uly="0" lrx="5704" lry="7744">
         <graphic url="https://iiif.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/amp/amp_0159/"/>
      </surface>
      <surface ulx="0" uly="0" lrx="5706" lry="7744">
         <graphic url="https://iiif.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/amp/amp_0160/"/>
      </surface>
      <surface ulx="0" uly="0" lrx="5708" lry="7744">
         <graphic url="https://iiif.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/amp/amp_0161/"/>
      </surface>
      <surface ulx="0" uly="0" lrx="5706" lry="7746">
         <graphic url="https://iiif.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/amp/amp_0162/"/>
      </surface>
      <surface ulx="0" uly="0" lrx="5708" lry="7748">
         <graphic url="https://iiif.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/amp/amp_0163/"/>
      </surface>
      <surface ulx="0" uly="0" lrx="5702" lry="7746">
         <graphic url="https://iiif.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/amp/amp_0164/"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text type="letter">
      <body>
         <div xml:id="transcription">
            <pb facs="https://iiif.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/amp/amp_0155/" type="sheet"/>
               <p>
                  (<unclear>1</unclear>
               </p>
               <p>
                  Sehr veehrter Herr Landeshauptmann,meine Damen und Herren:<lb/>
                  I hope you will pardon me if I speak somewhat personally. I do so,<lb/>
                  not out of vanity,but bec<del>ua</del>ause  I do <del>j</del>not wish to give the impression that I<lb/>
                  am attempting to lay down absolute laws which are valid for all. I give you my<lb/>
                  experiences as a poet,in the hope that you will be able to compare the<del>,</del>m with<lb/>
                  yours<del><unclear></unclear></del>,and form your own judgment about them.<lb/>
                  Most of what I <del><unclear>o</unclear></del>know about the writing of poetry,or at least about the kind I<lb/>
                  am interested in writing,I discovered long before I took any interest in poetry<lb/>
                  itself.<lb/>
                  Between the ages of six and twelve,I spent a great many of my waking hours in<lb/>
                  the fab<del>o</del>rication of a private secondary sacred world,the basic elements of which<lb/>
                  were <del>aft</del> a) a limestone landscape mainly derived from the Pennine Moors in the<lb/>
                  North of England and b) an industry - lead-mining.<lb/>
                  It is no doubt psychologically significant that my sacred world was autistic -<lb/>
                  that is to say,I had no wish to share it with others no<del>t</del>r could I have done so.<lb/>
                  However,though constructed for and inhabited by myself alone,I needed the help of<lb/>
                  others,my parents in particular,in collecting its basic materials; others had to<lb/>
                  procure for me the necessary text-books on geology and machinery,maps,catalog<del>i</del>ues,<lb/>
                  guide-books and photographs,and,when occasion offered<del>,to</del> ta<del>l</del>ke me down real mines,<lb/>
                  tasks which they performed with unfailing patience and generosity.<lb/>
                  From this activity,I learned certain principles which I was later to find applied<lb/>
                  to all artistic fabrication. First,whatever other elements it may include,the<lb/>
                  initial impulse to create a secondary world is a feeling of awe aroused by<lb/>
                  encounters,in the Primary World,with sacred beings or events.  This feeling of awe<lb/>
                  is an imperative,that is to<unclear>´</unclear> say,one is not free to choose the object or the event<lb/>
                  that arouses it. Though every work of art is a secondary world,it cannot be<lb/>
                  constructed ex nihilo,but is a selection from and a recombination of the contents of<lb/>
                  the Primary World. Even the 'purest' poem,in the French Symboliste sense,is<lb/>
                  made of words which are not the poet's private property,but the communal cre<unclear>a</unclear>tion<lb/>
                  of the linguistic group to whom he belongs,so that their meaning can be looked up<lb/>
                  in a dictionary.<lb/>
                  Secondly,in constructing my private world,I discovere<del>s</del>d that,though this was<lb/>
                  a game,or rather precisely because it was a game - that is to say,not a necessity<lb/>
                  like eating or sleeping,but something I was free to do or not as I chose - it<lb/>
                  could not be played without rules. Absolute freedom is meaningless: freedom can<lb/>
                  only be realised in a choice between alternati<del>c</del>ves. A secondary world,be it a poem,<lb/>
                  or a game of football or bridge,must be as much a world of law as the Primary,the<lb/>
                  only difference being that in the world of games one is free to decide what its<lb/>
                  laws shall be. But to all games as to real life,Goethe's lines apply.<lb/>
                  In der Beschränkung zeigt sich erst der Meister,<lb/>
                  Und d<del>s</del>as Gesetz nur kann uns Freiheit geben.<lb/>
                  As regards my particu<del>al</del>l<unclear>a</unclear>r lead-mining world,I decided,or rather,without conscious<lb/>
                  decision I instinctively felt,that I must impose two restrictions upon my freedom<lb/>
                  of fantasy. In choosing what objects were to be included,I was free to select this<lb/>
                  and reject that,on condition that both were real objects in the Primary World,to<lb/>
                  choose,for example,between two kinds of water-turbine,which could be found in a<lb/>
                  text-book  on mining machinery or a manufacturer's catalogue: but I was not free<lb/>
                  to invent one.  In deciding how my world was to function,I <del>was </del> could choose between<lb/>
                  t<del><unclear>e</unclear></del>wo practical possibilit<del>es</del>ies  - a mine can be drained either by an adit or a pump -<lb/>
                  but physic<del><unclear>s</unclear></del>al impossibili<del>es</del>ties and magic means were forbidden. <del><unclear>T</unclear></del>When I say forbidden,<lb/>
                  I mean that I felt,in some obscure way,that they were morally forbidden. Then there<lb/>
                  came a day when the moral issue became quite conscious. As I was planning my<lb/>
                  Platonic Idea of a concentrating-mill,I ran into difficulties. I had to choose<lb/>
                  between two types of a cer<del>at</del>tain machine for separating the sli<unclear>m</unclear>es,called a buddle.<lb/>
                  One type I found more sacred or '<del>beatiful</del> beautiful',but the other type was,I<lb/>
                  knew from my reading,the more efficient. At this point I realised that it was my<lb/>
                  moral duty to sacrifice my <del>aethetic</del> aesthetic preference to reality or truth.
               </p>
            <pb facs="https://iiif.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/amp/amp_0156/" type="sheet"/>
            <pb facs="https://iiif.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/amp/amp_0157/" type="sheet"/>
               <p>
                  (2
               </p>
               <p>
                  When,later,I began to write poetry&#x2019;I found that,for me,at least,the same<lb/><!-- any use in differentiating? -->
                  obligation was binding. That is to say,I cannot accept the do<del><unclear>s</unclear></del>ctrine that,in<lb/>
                  poetry,there is a 'suspension of belief<del><unclear>e</unclear></del>'. A poet must never make a statement<lb/>
                  simply because it sounds poetically exciting: he must also bel<del>ea</del>ieve it to be<lb/>
                  true. This does not mean,of course,that one can only appreciate a poet whose<lb/>
                  beliefs happen to co-incide with one's own. It does mean,however,that one must<lb/>
                  <del>n</del>be convinced that the poet really believ<del><unclear></unclear></del>es what he says,however odd <del>that</del> the<lb/>
                  belief may seem to oneself.<lb/>
                  Between constructing a private <del>fantsay</del>fantasy world for oneself alone<lb/>
                  and writing poetry,there is,of course,a profound difference. A <del>fanatsy</del><lb/>
                  fantasy world exists only in the head of its creator: a poem is a public<lb/>
                  verbal object intended to be read and enjoyed by others. To become conscious<lb/>
                  of others is to become conscious of historical time/. in various ways. The<lb/>
                  contents of a poem are necessarily past <del>expereinces</del> experiences,and the goal of<lb/>
                  a poem is <del>necessaily</del> necessarily in the future,since it cannot be read until<lb/>
                  it has been written. Again,to write a poem is to engage in an activity which<lb/>
                  human beings have practised for centuries. If one asks why human beings<lb/>
                  make poems or paint pictures or compose music,I can see two possible answers.<lb/>
                  Firstly all the artistic media are forms of an activity pecul<del>a</del>iar to human<lb/>
                  beings,namely,Personal Speech. Many animals have impersonal codes of<lb/>
                  communications,visual,olfactory,auditory signals,b<del><unclear></unclear></del>y which they convey to<lb/>
                  other members of their species vital information about food,territory,sex,<lb/>
                  the presence of <del>enmies</del> enemies etc,and in social animals like the bee,such<lb/>
                  a code may be exceedingly comple<del>s</del>x. We,too,of course,often use words in the same<lb/>
                  way,as when I ask a stranger the way to the railroad station. But when we<lb/>
                  truly speak,we do something quite different. We <del>spak</del> speak as person to person<lb/>
                  in order to disclose ourselves to others and share our exper<del>ei</del><unclear>i</unclear>ences with<lb/>
                  them,not because we must,but becuase we enjoy doing so. This activity is<lb/>
                  sometimes quite erroneously called 'self-expression'. If I write a poem<lb/>
                  about <del>ceratin</del> experiences I have had,I do so<del>,not bec</del> bec<del>ua</del>ause I think it<lb/>
                  <del>may</del>should be of interest and value to others<del>,not</del>: the fact that it has till now<lb/>
                  only been my exper<del>ei</del>ience is accidental. What the poet or any artist has to convey<lb/>
                  is a perception of a reality common to all,but seen from a unique perpsective,<lb/>
                  which it is his duty as well as his pleasure to share with others. To small<lb/>
                  truths as well as great,St Augustine's words apply.<lb/>
                  The truth is neither mine nor his nor another's;but belongs<lb/>
                  to us all whom Thou callest to partake of it: warning us<lb/>
                  terribly,not to account it private to ourselves,lest we be<lb/>
                  deprived of it.<lb/>
                  Then the second impulse to artistic fabrication is the desire to transcend<lb/>
                  our mortality,by making objects which,unlike ourselves,are not subject to<lb/>
                  natural death,but can remain <del>permantly</del> permanently 'on hand' in the world,<lb/>
                  long after we and our society have perished.<lb/>
                  Every genuine work of art,I believe,exhibits two qualities,Nowness and<lb/>
                  Permanence. By Nowness I mean the quality which enables an art-historian<lb/>
                  to date a work,at least,approximately. If,for example,one listens to<lb/>
                  a composition by Palestrina and one by Mozart,one knows immediately that,<lb/>
                  quite aside from their artistic merits,Palestrina must have lived earlier<lb/>
                  than Mozart: he could not possibly have written as he did after Mozart.<lb/>
                  By <del>P</del>perman<del>a</del>ence,I mean that the work continues to have relevance and<lb/>
                  importance lo<unclear>m</unclear>g after its creator is dead. In the history of Art,unlike<lb/>
                  the history of Science,no genuine work of art is made obsolete by a<lb/>
                  later work. Past science is of interest only to the historian of science,not<lb/>
                  to what scientists are doing at this moment. Past works of art,on the<lb/>
                  other hand,are of the utmost importance to the contemporary <del>praticioner<unclear>.</unclear></del><lb/>
                  practic<del>io</del>onerner. Every artist tries to produce something new,but in the hope<lb/>
                  that,in time,it will take its <del><unclear></unclear></del>proper place in the tradition of his art.<lb/>
                  And he cannot produce anything significantly original unless he knows<lb/>
                  well what has <del>been</del> already been done<unclear>;</unclear>w<del>ithout</del>,that is to say ,<del>even in</del> he cannot<lb/>
                  'rebel' against the past without having a profound reverence for it.
               </p>
            <pb facs="https://iiif.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/amp/amp_0158/" type="sheet"/>
            <pb facs="https://iiif.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/amp/amp_0159/" type="sheet"/>
               <p>
                  There are periods in history when xx the arts develop uninterruptedly,
                  each generation building on the achievements of the previous generation.
                  There are other periods when radical breaks seem to be necessary. However,
                  when they are, one will generally find that the 'radical' artist does not
                  disown the past, but finds in works of a much earlier period or ex
                  thosgof culture than his own, the clué to what he should do now.
                  In my own case, for example, I know how much I owe to Anglo-Saxon and
                  Medieval Poetry.
                  When I  review the contemporary artistic scene, it strikes me how
                  extraordinarily fortunate men like Stravinsky, Picasso, Eliot,
                  etc, that is, those persons we think of as the founders of 'modern' art,
                  were in being born when they were, so that they came to manhood before
                  I9I4. Until the x First World War, western society was still pretty much
                  what it had been in the nineteenth century. This meant that for these artists,
                  the felt need to create something new arose from an artistic imperative,
                  not a historic imperative. No one asked himself: "What is the proper
                  kind of music to compose or picture to paint or poem to write in the year
                  I9I2.?" Secondly, their  contemporary audiences, were mostly
                  conservative, but honestly so. Those,for instance, who were scandalised by
                  Le Sacre du Printemps,may seem to us now to have been old fogies, but
                  their reaction was genuine. They did not say to themselves: "Times have
                  changed and we must change with them in order xx not to
                  be left behind."
                  Here are a few statements by Stravinsky to  which the young,
                  artists or critics would do well to listen and x ponder over.
                  tether
                  In my youth the new music grew out of, and in reaction to, traditions,
                  whereas it appears to be evolving to-day as much from social needs
                  as interior artistic ones...The status of  new music as a
                  category is another incomparable. It had none at all in my early
                  years, being in fact categorically opposed,and often with real
                  hostility. But the unsuccess of composers of my generation at
                  least kept them from trading on success, and our unsuccess may have
                  been less insidious than the automatic superlatives which nowadays
                  kill the new by absorbing it to death.
                  
                  The use of the new hardware naturally appears to the new musician
                  as "historically imperative"; but music is made out of musical
                  imperatives, and the awareness of historical processes is probably
                  best left to future and different kinds of wage-earners.
                  
                  In times,like our own,of rapid social change and political crisis, there is
                  always a danger of confusing the principles governing political action and
                  those governing artistic fabrication. The most important of such confusmions
                  are three.
                  Firstly, one may come to, think of artistic fabrication as a f of political
                  action. Every citizen,  included, has a duty to be politically 'engage'
                  that is, to play a responsible part in seeing that the society of which
                  he is a member shall function properly and improve. But the poet, qua poet,
                  has only one political function. elanguage is his medium, it is his duty,
                  by his own example, to defend his mõtr-tongue against corruption by demagogues,
                  journalists,the mass-media etc. As Karl Kraus said: „Die Sprache ist die 
                  Mutter, nicht das Magd, des  Gedankens", and when language loses its meaning,
                  its  place is taken by violence. Of course,the poet may use poltical and
                  social events as subject-matter for poems - they are as much a part of human
                  experience as love or nature - but he must never imagine that his poems have
                  the power to affect the course of history. The politic al and social history
                  of Europe weuld be what it xx has been if Dante, Shakepeare, Goethe, Michale
                  Angelo, Titman, Mozart, Beethoven, ec, had never existed.
               </p>
            <pb facs="https://iiif.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/amp/amp_0160/" type="sheet"/>
            <pb facs="https://iiif.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/amp/amp_0161/" type="sheet"/>
               <p>
                  4
                  Where political and social  evils are concerned,only
                  two things are effectiver political action and straightforward, truthful,
                  detailed journalistic rapportage of the facts. The Arts are powerless.
                  The second confusion, of which Plato is the most famous example, is to take
                  artistic fabrication as the model for a good society. 
                  Such a model,if put into practice, is bound to produce a tyrrany. The aim of
                  the artist is to produce an object which is complete and will endure without
                  change.  In the 'city' of a poem,there are always the same inhabitants doing
                  exactly the same jobs for ever. A society which was really like a good poem,
                  embodying the aesthetic virtues of order, economy and subordination of the detail
                  to the whole, would be a nightmare of horror for, given the historical reality of
                  actual men, such a society could come into being through selective breeding,
                  exxermination of the physically and mentally unfit, absolute obedience to
                  its Birector, a alrge slave claas kept out of sight in Gellars and the
                  strictest censufehip of the Arts, forbidding anything to be said which xx is
                  out of keeping with the official 'line.
                  The third confusion, typical of our western  'free'
                  societies at this time,is the opposite of Plato's,namely to take political
                  action as the model for artistic fabrication. Political action is a necessity,
                  that is to say, a very moment something has to be done, and it
                  is momentary - action at this moment is immeiately followed by another action
                  at the next. Artistic fabrication, on the other hand, is  voluntary¬
                  the alternative to one work of art can be no work of art - and the artistic
                  object is permanent, that is to say, immune to historical change. The attempt
                  to model artistic fabrication os political action can therefore,only
                  reduce it to momentary and arbitrary 'happenings', a conformism with
                  the tyrrany of the immediate moment which is far more enslaving and
                  11
                  uescht
                  destructive of integrity than any conformism with past tradition.
                  What then, can the Arts do for us? In my opinion, they can do two things.
                  e
                  They can, as Dr Johnson said,'enable us a little better to enjoy life or a
                  little better to e it". And, because they are objects
                  permanently on hand in the world, they are the chief means by which the
                  living are able to break bread with the dead, and, without a communication
                  with the dead, I do not believe that a fully human civilised life is possible.
                  Perhaps, too, in our age, the mere making of a work of art is itself a
                  political act. So long as artists exist,making what they please or think
                  they ought to make, even if their works are not terribly good,they
                  remind the Management of something managers need to be reminded of, namely,
                  that the managed are people with faces, not anonymous numbers, that Homo
                  Laborans is also Homo Ludens.
                  And now, I hope those of you who know no English will forgive me is
                  I concludet these remarks with a light poem of my own, entitled
                  Doggerel  by a Senior Citizen.
               </p>
            <pb facs="https://iiif.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/amp/amp_0162/" type="sheet"/>
            <pb facs="https://iiif.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/amp/amp_0163/" type="sheet"/>
               <p>
                  At this point, a little digression on the subject of 'free' verse, which
                  seems now to be almost universal among young poets. Though excellent
                  examples, the poems of D.H.Lawrence, for example, exist, in my opinen they are, - we, dene
                  the exception, not the rule. The great virtue of formal metrical rules is
                  that they forbid automatic  responses and, by forcing the poet
                  to have second thoughts, free im foxm the fetters of self. All too often, the
                  result of not having a fixed form to be true to, is a self-indulgence which in
                  the detached reader can only cause boredom. Further, in my experence ,contrary
                  to what one might expect, the xx free-verse poets sound much more
                  like each other than those who write in fixed forms. Whatever freedom may do,
                  it does not, it would seem,make for originality.
               </p>
            <pb facs="https://iiif.acdh.oeaw.ac.at/amp/amp_0164/" type="sheet"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>